Guide to the Rafa Nasiri and May Muzaffar Collection AD.MC.092
al Mawrid Arab Art Archive, NYU Abu Dhabi
- Series III: Writings
  - III.A. Rafa Nasiri's Journals
    Handwritten and hand-illustrated diaries by Rafa Nasiri, created within bound journals and sketchbooks throughout his life, spanning 1976 to 2013. These feature sketches alongside observations of daily life, activities, and art events he attended. The almost daily entries were not separate from the art and ideas that were translated as drawings in the same cherished notebooks. They offer insight into the inner worlds of the artist, including his experiences of travels and war events. Nasiri recorded details about meetings with fellow artists and intellectuals in Baghdad, Asilah, Irbid, Amman, Beirut, and in Italy, Spain, the UAE, and other countries, students and teachers he worked with at Yarmouk University and the University of Bahrain, the routes he commuted on, his feelings towards personal and professional engagements, sketches of artifacts he saw in collections, his opinions on the quality of the lectures he attended and their audiences, and more.
    - 1. Paris, 1976, cuid352
    - 2. Journal that includes notes by May Muzaffar, c. 1982, cuid353
    - 3. Graphic Center, 1984–1985, cuid354
    - 4. Journal, multiple dates, cuid355
    - 5. Baghdad-Roma, 1988, cuid356
    - 6. Morocco, August 1990, cuid357
    - 7. Journal, Amman and Irbid, 1992–1993, cuid358
    - 8. Irbid, Jordan, 1.11.1993, cuid359
    - 9. Journal of Sharjah and Abu Dhabi Visit, 2000 and 2001, cuid360
    - 10. Bahrain journal, 2000, cuid361
    - 11. Bahrain journal, 2002, cuid362
    - 12. Cité Internationale des Arts, Paris, and Lisbon, 2008, cuid363
    - 13. Beirut journal, 2010, cuid364
    - 14. Baghdad and Amman journal, 2010, cuid365
    - 15. Istanbul journal, 2011, cuid366
    - 16. Jabal al Weibdeh notebook 1, Amman, 2011, cuid367
    - 17. Atlal, Baghdad + Cordoba, Jabal al Weibdeh notebook, Amman, 2011 (2), cuid368
    - 18. Jabal al Weibdeh notebook, Amman, 2012 (1), cuid369
    - 19. Jabal al Weibdeh notebook, Amman, 2012 (2), cuid370
    - 20. Studio Nasiri, 2013, cuid371
  - III.B. Rafa Nasiri's Writings, cuid372
    Lectures, texts and notes authored in Arabic by Rafa Nasiri on topics related to contemporary Arab and Iraqi art, graphic art practices, and inspirations for his work, as well as artist statements. Includes versions of texts titled "[Contemporary Arab Graphic Art,]" one of which was presented in a roundtable discussion in Bahrain in 2001, and "[Resistance through Creativity]" published in Al-Majallah Al-Thaqafiyyah [Cultural Magazine] in 2010.
  - III.C. May Muzzafar's Writings, cuid373
    Writings, reviews and notes by poet and critic May Muzaffar produced in Baghdad, Amman, and Manama starting from the 1970s.
  - III.D. Writings by Others, cuid374
    Includes clipped texts about Nasiri by writers and artists such as Jabra Ibrahim Jabra, Jacques Aswad, Farouq Yousef, Adel Kamel, Shaker Hassan Al Said, Ziad Dalloul, Dia al-Azzawi, and Abdel Wahhab al-Bayati, as well as texts on other topics and exhibitions that Nasiri collected, mostly from 1990s and 2000s
- Series IV: Exhibition Materials
  Reflecting Nasiri and Muzaffar's active participation in the art scenes in the cities in which they lived or visited, this series features numerous invitation cards and catalogs for exhibitions. It includes exhibitions organized by Rafa Nasiri in Arab cities, from 1975 to 2013. It also includes materials from group exhibitions with Iraqi artists from 1965 to 2009, and catalogs and price lists from exhibitions by fellow artists organized from 1980 to 2008.
  - IV.A. Rafa Nasiri's Solo Exhibitions
    - 1. "Rafa Nasiri, Graphics — Paintings," 1975, cuid375
    - 2. "Nasiri," Kuwait, 1976, cuid376
    - 3. "Variations of the Horizon," Baghdad, 1979, cuid377
    - 4. "[Rafa Nasiri]," Baghdad, 1979, cuid378
    - 5. "Nasiri," Amman, 1981, cuid379
    - 6. "Nasiri," Baghdad, 1984, cuid380
    - 7. "Nasiri," Casablanca, 1987, cuid381
    - 8. "Nasiri, Works on Paper," Baghdad, 1992, cuid382
    - 9. "Nasiri," Amman, 1994, cuid383
    - 10. "Nasiri, Paintings – Graphics," Bahrain, 1996, cuid384
    - 11. "Rafa Nasiri, Homage to al-Mutanabi," Bahrain, 2002, cuid385
    - 12. "Being in the Moment," Bahrain, 2013, cuid386
  - IV.B. Rafa Nasiri's Group Exhibitions
    - 1. "Iraqi Artists' Society, Eighth Annual Art Exhibition," Baghdad, 1965, cuid387
    - 2. "5: Rafa al-Nasiri - Saleh al-Jumaie - Dia al-Azzawi - Tarik Ibrahim - Maki Hussein," Baghdad, 1972, cuid388
    - 3. "3: Nasiri - Jumaie - Azzawi," Baghdad, 1975, cuid389
    - 4. "Untitled," Baghdad, 1979, cuid390
    - 5. "Exhibition of Contemporary Iraqi Art," Nicosia, 1990, cuid391
    - 6. "[Figures of Contemporary Iraqi Painting: Azzawi - Nasiri - Talib - Muhreddin]," circa 1993, cuid392
    - 7. "5 Visual Interpretations from Modern Iraqi Art," Dubai, 1997, cuid393
    - 8. "Azzawi - Nasiri," Paris, 1998, cuid394
    - 9. "Ali Taleb - Rafe' Nasiri," Amman, 1992, cuid395
    - 10. "Improvisation: An Exhibition of the Works of Seven Iraqi Artists," Amman, 2005, cuid396
    - 11. "Iraqi Artists in Exile," 2008–2009, cuid397
  - IV.C. Exhibitions by Other Artists
    - 1. "The First National Art Exhibition for Arab Women Artists," Baghdad, 1980, cuid398
    - 2. "Pioneers and Artists of the 1950's," 1992, cuid399
    - 3. "Ali Taleb," Beirut, 1994, cuid400
    - 4. "Duets, Quartets, and a Triangle: An Exhibition of the Recent Works by Kamal Boullata", Amman, 1994, cuid401
    - 5. "[Pioneers of Iraqi Painting]," Amman, 2001, cuid402
    - 6. "50 Years of Creation of Shaker Hasan Al Said," 2005, cuid403
    - 7. "[In Tribute to the Great Iraqi Painter Shaker Hassan Al Said]," Tunis, 2005, cuid404
    - 8. "[For Shaker Hassan Al Said]," Paris, 2005, cuid405
    - 9. "M. Muhreddin," Amman, 2008, cuid406
    - 10. [Iraq–Architectural Memory], Amman, cuid407
  - IV.D. Price Lists, 1995–2015, cuid408
    Includes price lists for group exhibitions in which Rafa Nasiri participated, in 1995 and 2005; for a solo exhibition for Shaker Hassan Al Said in 1995; for Mohammed Muhreddin in 2008; for Resmi Al Kafaji in 2015.
- Series V: Photographic Prints
  This series includes personal photographs for May Muzaffar and Rafa Nasiri from their childhood and adulthood years until Rafa Nasiri's late years when he was a cancer patient, as well as professional photographs covering Baghdad's social and artistic milieu from the 1960s to the 1990s. The collections show the couple's different houses in Baghdad, including meetings and gatherings at each one of them, interiors at the Institute of Fine Arts, trips made with friends around Iraq, meals and events with friends and guests, travel to Morocco, Germany, Portugal, and other countries, and Nasiri's Graphic Studio. During the Iran-Iraq War, Nasiri's Graphic Studio, known as Al Muhtaraf, was actively printing works for Nasiri and his fellow artists while also presenting exhibitions, keeping the art scene in Baghdad alive despite the grimness of war. Additional photos pertain to Nasiri and Muzaffar's years of exile in Amman and Manama from 1991 to 2013.
  - V.A. May Muzaffar, 1940s–1973, cuid409
    Photographs of May Muzaffar from her childhood, family, education, college years, and early active years as a young poet. The subseries also includes images from her workplace at the Iraq Reinsurance Company and trips with literary figures to poetry festivals in Iraq
  - V.B. Rafa Nasiri, 1940s–1973, cuid410
    Photographs of Rafa Nasiri from his childhood, family, education in Iraq and abroad, artistic initiatives and groups, his education at the Institute of Fine Arts, Baghdad, his printmaking training at the Central Academy of Fine Arts in Beijing (1959–1963), his diploma years in Portugal.
  - V.C. Rafa and May Muzaffar's Wedding, Baghdad, December 31, 1973, cuid411
  - V.D. Homes in Iraq, 1974–1991
    Photographs of the two houses where May Muzaffar and Rafa Nasiri lived in Baghdad, one in the Al Qadisiyah neighborhood, 1974–1985, and the other in al-Khadra neighborhood, 1985–1991. The photographs show the interiors, furniture, printing press, library, and art housed in their residences.
    - 1. Al Koukh (The Cottage), ‬Al Qadisiyah, Baghdad, 1974–1985, cuid412
    - 2. House in al-Khadra, Baghdad, 1985–1991, cuid413
  - V.E. Time in Iraq, 1974–1991, cuid414
    General photos from the couple's life and work in Baghdad between 1974 (first year of marriage) until 1991, when they relocated from Iraq to Jordan. Includes images of gatherings at their house in Al Khadra neighborhood, Nuha al-Radi's house, Maath Alousi's house in Baghdad, exhibitions and events at the Al Riwaq Gallery (1986), as well as trips around Iraqi towns and archeological sites.
  - V.F. Nasiri Graphic Studio, "Al Muhtaraf Nasiri," 1986–1989, cuid415
    Photographs of interiors and events taking place at Nasiri Graphic Studio (aka Al Muhtaraf Nasiri) in the Al-Mansour neighborhood in Baghdad. These events included lectures and exhibitions such as one for artist Ismail Fattah.
  - V.G. Travels, 1974–2013
    Photographs compiled by the couple from their solo or joint travels for purposes of participating in exhibitions, symposiums, conferences, residencies, tourism, and other. The pictures also feature the couple's arrival at the moment of the announcement of an award for Nasiri at the Norwegian International Print Biennale, Fredrikstad, in 1978, encounters with Arab and international artists and intellectuals such as Mahmoud Darwish and Nizar Qabbani, and images of European and Arab cities they have visited.
    - 1. The Graphic Art Exhibition at The Gravura, Lisbon, 1968, cuid416
    - 2. Salzburg, 1974, Berlin c.1986, cuid417
    - 3. 4th Norwegian International Print Biennale, Fredrikstad, 1978, cuid418
    - 4. Italy, undated, cuid419
    - 5. Rafa Nasiri exhibition at Sultan Gallery, c. 1980s, cuid420
    - 6. Rafa Nasiri in Berlin, c.1987, cuid421
    - 7. Madrid, 1989, cuid422
    - 8. Trips to Asilah, Morocco, with extension to Europe, Paris, Avignon, Athens, Madrid, 1979–1992, cuid423
    - 9. Beirut, 2010, cuid424
    - 10. Wadi Rum, Jordan, undated, cuid425
    - 11. Copenhagen, Amsterdam, and Istanbul, undated, cuid426
    - 12. France and United Kingdom, and Greece, undated, cuid427
    - 13. Unknown Location, likely Kurdistan, Iraq, undated, cuid428
  - V.H. Homes in Jordan and Bahrain, 1991–2013
    Photographs of the interiors of the couple's residences outside of Iraq, namely in a one-bedroom apartment on campus of Yarmouk University in Jordan (1991-1997), and a villa near the University of Bahrain in 1997. The pictures show the interiors, furniture, guests and Nasiri's artworks housed in their residences.
    - 1. Campus of Yarmouk University, Irbid, 1991–1997, cuid429
    - 2. 3rd Circle, Jabal Amman, 1992, cuid430
    - 3. 5th Circle, Jabal Amman, 1992–1995, cuid431
    - 4. Sweifieh, Amman, 1995–2000, cuid432
    - 5. Manama, Bahrain, 1997–2003, cuid433
    - 6. Shmeisani, Amman, 2000–2005, cuid434
    - 7. 4th Circle, Jabal Amman, 2005–now, cuid435
  - V.I. Jordan, 1991–2013
    - 1. Rafa Nasiri with students in Jordan, 1992, cuid436
    - 2. Art events in Amman, 1992 and 2001, cuid437
    - 3. Rafa Nasiri and George Bahgoury in Amman, c.2000s, cuid438
  - V.J. Bahrain, 1997–2003, cuid439
  - V.K. Undated Artworks by Rafa Nasiri and Other Artists, cuid493
    Numerous works in this subseries appear to have been created during the cultural seasons in Asilah, Morocco, some in 1979 and others in 1984.
- Series VI: Photographic Slides
  Sets of 35 mm photographic slides, mostly compiled into series by artist Rafa Nasiri, of exhibitions in Iraq and at international galleries and museums between the 1960s and 1990s. Some slides feature the artist's solo and group travels inside and outside Iraq. Some are from joint events and tours with Muzaffar in Morocco, Spain, Portugal, Germany, and others.
  - VI.A. Artworks and Exhibitions
    - 1. Unidentified exhibition, 1968, cuid440
    - 2. Rafa Nasiri's artworks, c. 1970–1977, some photographed in the artist's studio, Baghdad, cuid441
    - 3. Photograph of a mural, 1970, cuid442
    - 4. Artworks by Polish artists and designers, c.1975, cuid443
    - 5. Photographs of Baghdad International Poster Exhibition, 1977, cuid444
    - 6. Photographs of Art for Palestine poster exhibition, 1978, cuid445
    - 7. Exhibition at the Museum of Modern Art in Baghdad, 1978, cuid446
    - 8. Camp David Exhibition, 1979, cuid447
    - 9. Solo exhibition at Galerie Faris, Paris, 1983, cuid448
    - 10. Solo exhibition, Riwaq Gallery, Baghdad, 1984, cuid449
    - 11. Artworks by Rafa Nasiri and other artists, cuid450
    - 12. Artworks from the French Graphics Art Collection, n.d., cuid451
  - VI.B. Personal Spaces, Studio and Events in Iraq
    - 1. Portraits of Rafa Nasiri in 1965, 1966, 1971, cuid452
    - 2. Rafa Nasiri and May Muzaffar's home in Baghdad, 1976, cuid453
    - 3. Still life and wall details, 1977, cuid454
    - 4. Rafa Nasiri in studio, Baghdad, 1977, cuid455
    - 5. Rafa Nasiri studio, Baghdad, 1980s, cuid456
    - 6. Gathering in Baghdad and Rafa Nasiri's studio, cuid457
    - 7. Artist's mother and Ali Taleb in the city of Anah, Iraq, 1983, cuid458
    - 8. Studio space and artworks at the artist home, Baghdad, 1978, cuid459
    - 9. Rafa Nasiri's mural in Nineveh Hotel Oberoi, Mosul, Iraq, 1980s, cuid460
    - 10. Photographic prints of Rafa Nasiri solo exhibition at Riwaq Gallery, Baghdad, 1986, cuid461
    - 11. Burnt slides, cuid462
  - VI.C. Travels
    Photographic slides of Rafa Nasiri's travels between 1965 and 1993, including numerous road trips made with his brothers, residencies in Asilah, trips in Europe and East Asia, and trips in Iraq, Jordan and India.
    - 1. Photographs of sites worldwide, 1965–1969, cuid463
    - 2. Rafa Nasiri in Spain, Morocco, Algeria, and Libya (Tripoli), 1965, cuid464
    - 3. Rafa Nasiri in trips including one to Jerusalem, Palestine, c. 1965–1966, cuid465
    - 4. Close ups from archaeological sites, 1970–1971, cuid466
    - 5. Photographs of travels in Spain and Portugal, 1977, cuid467
    - 6. May Muzaffar and Rafa Nasiri in Sweden, 1978, cuid468
    - 7. Rome (Vatican and the Spanish Steps), 1979, cuid469
    - 8. Travel to Brazil, 1979, cuid470
    - 9. Two sets of photographs of travel in the UK, one of which is to the Cornwall Coast, 1981, cuid471
    - 10. Trip to Salzburg, Austria, 1982, cuid472
    - 11. India, 1986, cuid473
    - 12. Photographs of of Sheikh Lotfallah Mosque and Shah Mosque in Isfahan, Iran; and photos in India, cuid474
    - 13. Travels to Beijing and Seoul, 1989, cuid475
    - 14. Slides from around Iraq and other, 1989, cuid476
    - 15. Slides of artists in Morocco (Asilah) and Spain, 1990 and other years, cuid477
    - 16. Rafa Nasiri in Amman and at Darat al Funun, c.1993, cuid478
    - 17. Archaeological sites in Jerash, Jordan, n.d., cuid479
    - 18. Different trips to Dresden and other cities in Europe, n.d., cuid480
    - 19. Trip to Bashiqa, Kurdistan, n.d., cuid481
    - 20. Assyrian ruins, Iraq, n.d., cuid482
    - 21. Museum objects and motifs, n.d., cuid483
    - 22. Travel to Berlin, n.d., cuid484
- Series VII: Designs by or Featuring Rafa Nasiri
  A collection of cards and pamphlets, either designed by Rafa Nasiri or published in a series with connection to him. Some cards were published by Nasiri Graphic Studio (aka Al Muhtaraf Nasiri) in the Al-Mansour neighborhood in Baghdad in the 1980s and 1990s, some reference the artist's Jordanian address in Amman and Irbid, and some were produced by the Iraqi Cultural Center in London in the 1970s, commissioned by the General Federation of Iraqi Women (c.1979), Iraq Reinsurance Company (n.d.), or the Ministry of Information in Baghdad.
  - VII.A. Cards and Pamphlets Designed by Rafa Nasiri, 1977 to 1996, cuid485
  - VII.B. Cards Produced at Nasiri Graphic Studio (Al Muhtaraf Nasiri), Al-Mansour, Baghdad, 1990, cuid486
  - VII.C. Other Cards and Designs, cuid487
- Series VIII: Other Items in the Possession of the Artist
  Preparatory material for the book Story of Water and Fire; holiday cards, stamps, a set of flashcards with notes from Rafa Nasiri, holiday postcards, and a 2005 calendar.
  - VIII.A. Preparatory Material for Book Story of Water and Fire (postcards, letters and photographs), cuid488
  - VIII.B. Holiday Cards and Postcards, cuid489
  - VIII.C. Packet of Stamps, cuid490
  - VIII.D. Set of Flashcards with Notes from Rafa Nasiri, cuid491
  - VIII.E. Calendar, 2005, cuid492